A Guide to the Home Interest Club Records, 1903-2005
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Home Interest Club Records 1903-2005
Thomas Balch Library
M 077, VC 0050, ART 0004
This collection is made up of the administrative papers of the Home Interest Club. Records include correspondence, financial records, meeting agendas and minutes, as well as some of the notes for presentations made by members at the monthly meetings. Presentations made by Rachel Hoge Branch (1875-1944), one of the founding members, have been photocopied and collected in a bound volume by her son. The volume, included here, is titled Papers from Overlea. There are handwritten recipes contributed by the membership, some of them dating to the founding of the club. The recipes have been arranged thematically in preparation for the production of a cookbook in 2003, a copy of which is also included in the collection. Also of note in the collection are yearbooks, which contain the names of the officers for the year, a list of meetings, and brief descriptions of the meeting presentations. It was common for the yearbooks to be bound in scraps of wallpaper. The collection includes a small set of photographs from three summer picnics, and a walnut button box that was used in the election of new members to the club.
Home Interest Club, Purcellville, VA.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Home Interest Club, Purcellville, VA.
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2001.0007
Historical Information
The Home Interest Club was founded in the fall of 1903 by a group of women near Lincoln, VA and continues to operate. Most of the founding women were members of the Society of Friends, though involvement with the Friends was not a prerequisite for membership in the club. The constitution and bylaws of the club state that it is to "Benefit the home by making housekeeping easier in the exchanging of recipes and the discussion of all topics tending to elevate and improve the home." One of the original requirements of membership was that every woman share a proven recipe at each meeting. Some of the recipes were eventually published in a cookbook written to celebrate the centennial anniversary of the founding of the club, a copy of which is included in the club's records.
Some of the early members of the club included:
Rachel Hoge Branch (1875-1944)
Elizabeth Brown (1822-1904)
Lydia Brown (1845-1926)
Rebecca Brown (1858-1938)
Mary Gregg (1853-1923)
Virginia Hirst (1857-1936)
Clara Hoge (1865-1947)
Julia B. Hoge (1880-1929)
Laura Hoge (1867-1942)
Cosmelia Janney Hughes (1872-1962)
Cosmelia Janney (1858-1940)
Caroline Pancoast (1873-1950)
The club holds monthly meetings that throughout its history have consisted of a roll call, discussion of club business, a program, and refreshments. The program usually consists one or more presentations by members. Presentations may include readings from published material or original writings, but are usually informational in nature. Topics have included temperance, suffrage for women, civil rights for African Americans, foreign affairs, local history, and current events. During World War II there was a program on using sugar substitutes and members were asked to contribute sugar-shortage recipes. The membership also shares ideas about education, child rearing, and household maintenance.
Initially, membership was capped at twenty, though in 1936 the club amended its constitution to allow thirty. When a membership becomes available in the club, an active member nominates a woman. Her name is brought before the club at a meeting, and each member votes to approve or deny the nominated woman. Balloting was done originally using a button box and white and black buttons. A white button placed in the box was a vote to approve the nomination, while a black button denied membership. The club's constitution stipulates that approval be unanimous. The button box was eventually retired in favor of a secret ballot; currently the club uses a vocal vote. New officers are elected each fall and take their posts in January.
The club works with other organizations in the community to raise money for and awareness of issues affecting women and children. It has collaborated with the Paxton Home for Children, Hamilton Book Club, Purcellville Woman's Club, and Leesburg Garden Club on various projects in the community. The Home Interest Club remains active and continues to donate resources and energy to projects to improve the Loudoun County community.
Scope and Content
This collection is made up of the administrative papers of the Home Interest Club. Records include correspondence, financial records, meeting agendas and minutes, as well as some of the notes for presentations made by members at the monthly meetings. Presentations made by Rachel Hoge Branch (1875-1944), one of the founding members, have been photocopied and collected in a bound volume by her son. The volume, included here, is titled Papers from Overlea. There are handwritten recipes contributed by the membership, some of them dating to the founding of the club. The recipes have been arranged thematically in preparation for the production of a cookbook in 2003, a copy of which is also included in the collection. Also of note in the collection are yearbooks, which contain the names of the officers for the year, a list of meetings, and brief descriptions of the meeting presentations. It was common for the yearbooks to be bound in scraps of wallpaper. The collection includes a small set of photographs from three summer picnics, and a walnut button box that was used in the election of new members to the club. An explanation of the election procedure is located in Box 1.
Arrangement
Box: folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Ancestry Library Edition, United States Census, United States Census and Voter Lists, http://ww.ancestrylibrary.com (Accessed 7 November 2012).
"Home club celebrates centennial." Loudoun Times-Mirror, 10 September 2003, A2.
Home Interest Club Records, 1903-2005 (M 077). Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Loudoun Cemetery Database, http://www.leesburgva.gov/index.aspx?page=940 accessed, 7 November 2012.
Loudoun County Newspaper Index, http://www.leesburgva.gov/Modules/ ShowDocument.aspx?documentid=5574 accessed, 8 November 2012.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
Cosmelia Janney Hughes Sketchbook, 1945 (BV 007). Jane Hirst Bogle Photograph Collection (VC 0005). Leesburg Garden Club Collection, 1920- (M 044). Purcellville Woman's Club, 1922-1960 (M 046). A Taste of Loudoun County: Our Favorite Recipes, 1903-1951, compiled by George A. Hrunenei, 2003 (V REF 641.5975 HOM).
Contents List
- (M 077)
- (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1969
  - Cookbook, A Taste of Loudoun County: Our Favorite Recipes, 1903-1951. Centennial Edition, Compiled by George A. Hruneni, 2003
  - Cookbook Recipes:
    - Frozen Desserts, Breads
    - Cakes
    - Vegetables, Miscellaneous, Chicken
    - Soups, Salad Dressings, Cookies
    - Candies, Pudding, Pickles
  - Correspondence, n.d., 1904-1992
  - Election procedure, May 2003
  - Financial Records:
    - Account Books, 1905-1924; 1966-1969
    - Bank Statements, 1964-1969
    - Cancelled Checks, 1964-1969
- (Box 2)
  - Financial Records:
    - Checkbooks (Purcellville National Bank and First National Bank of Purcellville), 1960s
    - Treasurer's Book, 1958-1963
  - Meeting Agendas, 1906-1953
  - Meeting Minutes, 1920-1960
- (Box 3)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1961-2004
  - Meeting Presentations, n.d.; 1908; 1935; 1941
  - Membership and Officer Lists, 1933; 1952; 1981-2005
  - Newspaper Clippings, n.d.; 1912-1989
- (Box 4)
  - Outside Organizations:
    - Loudoun Abused Women's Shelter, n.d.; 1991-1992
    - Loudoun County Public Library Foundation, 1985
    - Purcellville Women's Club, 1908; 1913
  - "Papers from Overlea," by Rachel Hoge Branch (A bound collection of presentations delivered at the Home Interest Club meetings), 1977 and 1991
  - Yearbooks, 1962-2002
- (VC 0050)
  - 15 photographs of summer picnics, 1995, 1997, 2000
- (ART 0004)
  - 1 walnut button box, c. 1903